<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<init>
  <chapter name="Introduction" >
    <text>    Hello!

     Here is a Go language interactive tutorial, interactive - because you can edit the code and then execute it immedeately to see the results of your changes.

     The tutorial is very simple to navigate, it has minimum of tools. Just click on a tree node to see appropriate content in a text editor. If this is a code fragment, clicking on a '>' button, which is in a right top corner of a window above the editor will execute this code. The "Fmt" button uses gofmt program to format the code in the editor window. '+', '-' buttons are intended to increase/decrease a font size in the editor window.

     Thanks for your attention.
     Alexander S.Kresin.

    </text>
  </chapter>
  <chapter name="A Tour of Go" >
    <text>This is an abbreviated Tour of Go from the official cite: https://tour.golang.org/welcome/1
    </text>
    <chapter name="Basics" >
      <module name = "Packages">
        <code><![CDATA[/* Every Go program is made up of packages.
Programs start running in package main.
This program is using the packages with import paths "fmt" and "string".
By convention, the package name is the same as the last element of the
import path. For instance, the "math/rand" package comprises files that
begin with the statement package rand. */
package main

import (
	"fmt"
	"strings"
)

func main() {
	s := "test"
	n := strings.Index(s,"s")
	fmt.Println(s[:n])
	fmt.Println(s[n+1:])
}]]>
        </code>
      </module>
      <module name = "Exported names">
        <code><![CDATA[/* In Go, a name is exported if it begins with a capital letter. For example,
Pizza is an exported name, as is Pi, which is exported from the math package.
pizza and pi do not start with a capital letter, so they are not exported.
When importing a package, you can refer only to its exported names. Any
"unexported" names are not accessible from outside the package.
Run the code. Notice the error message.
To fix the error, rename math.pi to math.Pi and try it again. */
package main

import (
	"fmt"
	"math"
)

func main() {
	fmt.Println(math.pi)
}]]>
        </code>
      </module>
      <module name = "Functions">
        <code><![CDATA[/* A function can take zero or more arguments.
In this example, add takes two parameters of type int.
Notice that the type comes after the variable name.
When two or more consecutive named function parameters share a type, you can
omit the type from all but the last - as in sub() function in this example. */
package main

import "fmt"

func add(x int, y int) int {
	return x + y
}

func sub(x, y int) int {
	return x - y
}

func main() {
	fmt.Println(add(42, 13))
	fmt.Println(sub(42, 13))
}]]>
        </code>
      </module>
      <module name = "Multiple results">
        <code><![CDATA[/* A function can return any number of results.
The swap() function returns two strings. 
Go's return values may be named. If so, they are treated as variables
defined at the top of the function - see split() function.
These names should be used to document the meaning of the return values.
A return statement without arguments returns the named return values.
This is known as a "naked" return.
Naked return statements should be used only in short functions, as with
the example shown here. They can harm readability in longer functions. */
package main

import "fmt"

func swap(x, y string) (string, string) {
	return y, x
}

func split(sum int) (x, y int) {
	x = sum * 4 / 9
	y = sum - x
	return
}

func main() {
	a, b := swap("hello", "world")
	fmt.Println(a, b)
	fmt.Println(split(17))
}]]>
        </code>
      </module>
      <module name = "Variables">
        <code><![CDATA[/* The var statement declares a list of variables; as in function argument lists, the type is last.
A var statement can be at package or function level. We see both in this example.
A var declaration can include initializers, one per variable.
If an initializer is present, the type can be omitted; the variable
will take the type of the initializer.
Inside a function, the := short assignment statement can be used in place
of a var declaration with implicit type.
Outside a function, every statement begins with a keyword
(var, func, and so on) and so the := construct is not available. */
package main

import "fmt"

var c, python, java bool

func main() {
	var i, j = 1, 2

	x := 10
	fmt.Println(i, j, x, c, python, java)
}]]>
        </code>
      </module>
    </chapter>
  </chapter>
  <chapter name="Go by Example" >
    <text>This section contains code samples from the cite "Go by Example": https://gobyexample.com/
    </text>
  </chapter>
  <chapter name="External GUI" >
    <text>This section is about the External - GUI framework, based on using the GuiServer, external standalone application, which provides GUI service.
This program, Golang Tutor, is written, using this framework.
    </text>
    <module name = "Main window">
      <code><![CDATA[
package main

import (
	egui "github.com/alkresin/external"
)

func main() {

	if egui.Init("") != 0 {
		return
	}

	pWindow := &(egui.Widget{X: 100, Y: 100, W: 400, H: 280, Title: "External"})
	egui.InitMainWindow(pWindow)

	pWindow.Activate()
	egui.Exit()

}]]>
      </code>
    </module>
  </chapter>
</init>